<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief account of the rebellions and bloudshed occasioned by the anti-Christian practices of the Jesuits and other popish emissaries in the empire of Ethiopia collected out of a manuscript history written in Latin by Jo. Michael Wansleben, a learned papist.</title>
            <author>Wansleben, Johann Michael, 1635-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W710</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15140</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13144569</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13144569</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98035</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67490)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98035)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 780:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief account of the rebellions and bloudshed occasioned by the anti-Christian practices of the Jesuits and other popish emissaries in the empire of Ethiopia collected out of a manuscript history written in Latin by Jo. Michael Wansleben, a learned papist.</title>
                  <author>Wansleben, Johann Michael, 1635-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 37 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Jonathan Edwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Ethiopia.</term>
               <term>Ethiopia --  Church history.</term>
               <term>Ethiopia --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98035:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98035:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Rebellions and Bloudſhed</hi> Occaſioned by the <hi>Anti-Christian Practices</hi> OF THE JESUITS And other POPISH EMISSARIES IN THE EMPIRE OF ETHIOPIA. Collected out of a Manuſcript Hiſtory Written in Latin by <hi>JO. MICHAEL WANSLEBEN,</hi> a Learned Papiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Jonathan Edwin,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Three Roſes</hi> in <hi>Ludgate street,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:98035:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRIMATUR,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Geo. Thorp</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> in Chriſto P. &amp; D. D<hi rend="sup">no</hi> Guliel. Archiep. Cant. à Sacris Domeſticis.</signed>
               <dateline>Ex Aedib. Lambeth. <date>Jan. <hi>1. 1678/9.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98035:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>IN the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> which the <hi>Author of our Faith</hi> hath bequeathed us not only for a brief <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of Chriſtian Principles</hi> but an expreſs and unchangeable <hi>Rule of Practice</hi> too, the <hi>Wiſdom of the Father</hi> hath ſo admirably reconciled the Interests of GOD and MAN as well in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> as the <hi>Perſon</hi> of his <hi>Eternal Son,</hi> that while it conſults <hi>Glory to God on High,</hi> it doth no leſs conciliate <hi>Peace on Earth</hi> and <hi>Good Will among Men;</hi> all the Laws and Precepts thereof having ſuch a natural Tendency to ſuppreſs or regulate thoſe Humane Lusts and Paſſions which diſquiet the World, as might in reaſon procure the due and full Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of <hi>that Prediction,</hi> touching the Happy State of the <hi>Chriſtian Oeconomy</hi> under the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> which (according to the Inference <hi>Joſeph</hi> made from the Duplication of <hi>Pharaoh's Dream) for the greater certainty of the thing</hi> is <hi>twice</hi> recorded by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> in thoſe expreſs terms,<note place="margin">Gen. 41.32.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall beat their Swords into Plowſhares and their Spears into Prun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-hooks;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Nation ſhall not lift up ſword againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah 4.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>neither ſhall they learn War any more: but they ſhall ſit every man under his Vine and under his Fig-tree, and none ſhall make them afraid.</hi> And that <hi>the Spirit who ſpake by the Prophets</hi> might not differ from Himſelf in <hi>the Apoſtles,</hi> they impoſed not their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> upon the <hi>Gainſaying Pagans</hi> by <hi>Fire</hi> or <hi>Sword,</hi> nor ſowed <hi>Diſſention</hi> among <hi>Idolatrous People</hi> to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb facs="tcp:98035:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>their <hi>Converſion,</hi> but did at once preach and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the <hi>Will</hi> of their Master in <hi>Suffering the loſs of their own Lives</hi> (not conſpiring the <hi>Death</hi> of others) <hi>for his ſake;</hi> which won their Perſecutors to embrace the <hi>Faith</hi> they taught and dy'd for, being charmed by the Beauty and Excellence of <hi>that meek and quiet Spirit</hi> wherewith they did adorn and recommend it.</p>
            <p>Yet, as if the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> were not <hi>the ſame Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and to day,</hi> his pretended <hi>Vicar</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> ſends forth Emiſſaries, whoſe Zealand Industry to <hi>propagate the Faith</hi> which they would needs have to be <hi>Catholick,</hi> are employ'd after a far different Method to gain <hi>Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes;</hi> eſpecially thoſe who most glory in appropriating his <hi>Sacred Name</hi> to their <hi>Unhallowed Order;</hi> while, instead of conforming to the <hi>Goſpel-Precepts of Jeſus,</hi> they execute that Prophecy dictated by the <hi>Legal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>Joel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 3.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Proclaim ye this among the Gentiles; Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare War, wake up the Mighty men, let all the men of War draw near, let them come up. Beat your Plow-ſhares into Swords, and your Pruning-hooks into Spears.</hi> For, That Church or State which they fail of <hi>perverting</hi> by strength of <hi>Arguments,</hi> ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to utter <hi>ſubverſion</hi> by force of <hi>Arms:</hi> any Prince whom they cannot infect with their <hi>Superſtitious Principles</hi> had need beware lest he taste their <hi>Poiſon</hi> or feel their <hi>Poniard:</hi> What their <hi>Preaching</hi> or ſubtile <hi>Perſwaſions</hi> cannot effect, <hi>Plots, Treaſons, Murders, Tumults, Fire,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Unchriſtian Practices</hi> ſhall carry on.</p>
            <p>This is a Truth which more than one Age and Nation hath ſadly experienced, but none ever had more reaſon to abhor and deprecate than Ours. Yet the well-ordered Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our <hi>Britiſh</hi> Church and State is not the ſole
<pb facs="tcp:98035:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Object of <hi>Roman</hi> envy, nor hath <hi>England</hi> been the only Scene of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Cruelty. Not to mention the known and memorable Inſtances of <hi>Paris, Piedmont, Ireland</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> a Country little known and leſs frequented by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> hath felt the ſmart of <hi>Rome's</hi> malice, and bears freſh Scars of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Treachery; who (if they pleaſe to think it a Commendation) are no <hi>Changelings,</hi> but conſtant to their MORALS, having in all points approved themſelves the ſame in <hi>Africa</hi> which they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at this day in <hi>Europe;</hi> a Tranſcript as well of their preſent <hi>Deſigns</hi> as their former <hi>Plots</hi> againſt <hi>England,</hi> being delineated in this ſhort Abſtract of the <hi>Abiſſin Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did the <hi>Popiſh Emiſſaries</hi> foment a <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> to compaſs the Deſtruction of our Glorious Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr <hi>King Charles?</hi> The ſame they practiſed in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> not only to the great hazard of <hi>Adams Saghed,</hi> but the actual Ruine of <hi>Zà Dinghil,</hi> lawful Princes thereof.</p>
            <p>Have our Modern <hi>Jeſuits</hi> veiled <hi>Murder</hi> under the Covert of their <hi>Chappels</hi> or <hi>Altars</hi> here? There they raiſed <hi>Strongholds</hi> and <hi>Fortreſſes</hi> under the Pretence of building. <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Colledges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have they ſecretly prepared <hi>Fire-bals</hi> and other <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi> of Miſchief and Villany among us? In <hi>Abiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> they did alſo conceal Warlike Engines in their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Houſes.</p>
            <p>Have they drawn ſome of our <hi>Engliſh Subjects</hi> into the horrid <hi>Plot</hi> (lately diſcovered) againſt their <hi>Native Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrey?</hi> They did no leſs among the <hi>Abiſſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have they conſpired the Introducing of a <hi>Foreign Power</hi> into <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> They likewiſe not only Deſigned to betray the <hi>Ethiopick Empire</hi> to the
<pb facs="tcp:98035:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>King of <hi>Portugal;</hi> but through their <hi>Treaſonable Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices</hi> the <hi>Abiſſin Sea-coaſts</hi> are actually delivered into the hands of the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, Have they <hi>plotted</hi> to <hi>Aſſaſſinate</hi> our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord the King? So they did to <hi>kill</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror <hi>Adamas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet how exact ſoever the <hi>parallel</hi> is, I ſhall not preſume to recommend thoſe rigorous Proceedings found neceſſary to reſcue <hi>Ethiopia</hi> from this <hi>State peſt,</hi> as the fitteſt Precedent to remedy or prevent the preſent Danger of <hi>England;</hi> but (according to my Duty) leave theſe Myſteries of State to the judicious determination of His <hi>Gracious Majeſty</hi> and His <hi>Great Council,</hi> whom God preſerve and proſper.</p>
            <p>But leſt the Gate ſwell too big for the City, I refer my Reader for further ſatisfaction to the <hi>Narrative</hi> it ſelf, which may well be concluded <hi>impartial</hi> in what concerns the <hi>Jeſuits and other Popiſh Emiſſaries,</hi> ſince it comes from one of their own Profeſſion; whom I have not only render'd with all poſſible fidelity but (to prevent any juſt ground of Cavil on that ſcore) whatſoever the Coherence or Illuſtration of his Diſcourſe thus abbreviated, induced me to inſert, may eaſily be diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Authors own words,</hi> by thoſe Crotchets wherein <hi>mine</hi> are incloſed <hi>[thus]</hi> throughout the whole Tract.</p>
            <p>And if the <hi>Account</hi> here given (added to the many other <hi>Jeſuitical arts,</hi> which are now no longer a <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery)</hi> induce any man to become a Proſelyte to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cauſe</hi> or <hi>Party,</hi> I ſhall as little envy his <hi>Wit</hi> as I approve his <hi>Choice.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98035:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A BRIEF ACCOUNT OF THE <hi>Rebellions and Blondſhed</hi> Occaſioned by the <hi>ANTI-CHRISTIAN PRACTICES</hi> OF THE JESUITS And other POPISH EMISSARIES IN THE <hi>EMPIRE</hi> of <hi>ETHIOPIA.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Esfa Lion,</hi> a Native of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> in his cloſe to <hi>St. John</hi>'s Goſpel, which he publiſhed, together with the reſt of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> in his Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tongue (imprinted at <hi>Rome</hi> in the year of our Lord 1548.) affirms that his Soveraign's Anceſtors were in times paſt Lords of 62 Kingdoms, but their Empire is now reduced to a Third part of its ancient Dimenſions. [A vaſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which (though concealed in thoſe inward Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of <hi>Africa,</hi> neither well known nor oft fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented by us of <hi>Europe,</hi> yet) may claim a juſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98035:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>among all the Nations of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> not only for the large extent of its Dominions, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the prime Antiquity of its Converſion to the Chriſtian Faith, or at leaſt its early Notice and participation of that Goſpel whereby it hath been propagated in the World.</p>
            <p>For, ſhortly after the Glorious Aſcenſion of our Lord into Heaven, an Eunuch of great Authority un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Candace</hi> Queen of the <hi>Ethiopians</hi>] whom the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Tesfa Zion,</hi> without expreſſing by what Authority he doth it, names <hi>Lacaſa,</hi> and the place of her principal Reſidence <hi>Tigra</hi> [upon his return from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> whither he had come to worſhip, met with <hi>Philip</hi> the Evangeliſt in the Deſart of <hi>Gaza,</hi> who after he had preached unto him <hi>JESUS,</hi> in the Expoſition of what he then read in the Book of <hi>Eſaias</hi> the Prophet, baptized him in the next Water they came to as they went on their way; whereof we have an authentick Record in the <hi>8th.</hi> Chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Holy Apoſtles. And ſince the Spirit of Truth in the ſame Scripture tells us, <hi>He went on his way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing,</hi> doubtleſs at his journeys end he expreſſed that Joy and its juſt occaſion, in making a publick decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to his Countrey-men of all that befel him in the way, and ſo he became the firſt Preacher of the Goſpel to that part of the World, though he was not fully qualified to convey all the priviledges that might compleat the Foundation of the Chriſtian Church among them:] For,<note place="margin">Vid. Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan. An. Cbr. 35. N. 9. &amp; 15.</note> the Eunuch wanting the Authority of conferring Holy Orders, (in regard he receiv'd both his Baptiſm and Inſtruction from a <hi>Deacon</hi> only, and returned home without any Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> hands) the <hi>Abiſſins</hi> remained de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98035:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Prieſts or Biſhops till ſuch time as one <hi>Abà Seláma</hi> arrived in that Countrey; whereof<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory writes to this effect:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meropius</hi> a certain <hi>Tyrian</hi> Philoſopher determining to viſit <hi>India,</hi> took two Youths to accompany him in his Travels, the one named <hi>Aedeſius,</hi> the other <hi>Frumentius.</hi> In his Return he unhappily fell into a Port of <hi>Africa,</hi> where a barbarous people ſurprized him and his whole Company, and ſlew them all, except the two Lads whom they found Conning their Leſſons under a Tree near the inhoſpitable Harbor, and of theſe they made a Preſent to their Soveraign. <hi>Aedeſius</hi> was raiſed to the Office of his Cup-bearer, but he advanced <hi>Frumentius</hi> to be one of his Privy-Council. After that Monarchs death, <hi>Frumentius</hi> became Protector to the heir during his minority, in which time he made diligent Inquiry among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Merchants that drove a Traffick in thoſe parts for ſuch as were <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and theſe he directed and authorized to build divers magnificent Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures for the publick exerciſe of the <hi>Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> in more ſolemn Aſſemblies than had there been uſual afore-time. But when the young Prince arrived to ſuch years as qualified him to aſſume the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he no ſooner took the Scepter into his own hands, but <hi>Aedeſius</hi> returned to his Kindred at <hi>Tyre; Frumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> travelled to <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where after he had related the State of the Countrey from whence he came to the <hi>Patriarch,</hi> adviſing him to ſend ſome ſitper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thither endued with <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Dignity and Power, upon a Motion made by <hi>Athanaſius</hi> (then newly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Order of<note n="*" place="margin">An Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opick Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry written by <hi>P. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meyda</hi> ſaith be was Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch at that time. <hi>Ex Chron. Auzumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi.</hi>
               </note> Prieſthood) the ſame <hi>Fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentius</hi> was ſent back inveſted with the Authority
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98035:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a Biſhop, who not only encreaſed the number of Believers by the Apoſtolick Miracles, which he wrought, but eſtabliſhed alſo a Succeſſion of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Officers in thoſe Countreys: Whereupon the <hi>Abiſſins,</hi> in memory of the ſingular Benefits they received by his Miniſtry, ſtyled him <hi>Aba Seláma, i. e.</hi> The Father of Peace; [and have ever ſince honour'd the See of <hi>Alexandria</hi> with the Conſecration of their ſucceſſive Metropolitans.] According to the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Chronologies this came to paſs in the Year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 356. when two Brothers, whom they name <hi>Abri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Azbiha,</hi> raigned together: but<note n="*" place="margin">An. Chr. <hi>327.</hi> N. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Spondanus</hi> diſagrees in the Computation of the time, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Raign nine and twenty years ſooner.</p>
            <p>From this <hi>Aba Seláma,</hi> to <hi>Abuna Simon</hi> who died in the year 1618. they reckon up Ninety five Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitans in a continued Succeſſion.</p>
            <p>But the Church of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> thus planted and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the Orthodox Profeſſion of the Goſpel, did not long retain the Catholick Faith in its Purity: for, ſoon after the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> (which was convened in the year of Chriſt, 451.) had condemned <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> of Hereſie, from whom, being then Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> (or rather from <hi>Jacob Syrus</hi> his Scholar, according to their own Confeſſion) the <hi>Abiſſins</hi> receiv'd the corrupt Opinion of <hi>Eutyches;</hi> they did not only ſeparate from the Churches of <hi>Europe,</hi> but proceeded ſo far as to paſs ſentence of Excommunication againſt them, the form where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of my Author out of an Ethiopick Manuſcript which he found ſomewhere in <hi>England,</hi> tranſlates in theſe words, <hi>Maledicta ſit impia Synodus quoe</hi> Chalcedone <hi>habita eſt: Maledictus ſit qui cum illis communicat, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſque
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98035:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>qui in eâdem ſide cum illis permanent. Nos autem non obedimus Congregationi iſtoe hoereticoe unquam.</hi> In Engliſh thus. <q rend="inline">Let the wicked Synod held at <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> be accurſed: Curſed be he that is of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and all thoſe that continue in the ſame Faith with them. But we own no Obedience or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to that Heretical aſſembly.</q>
            </p>
            <p>From that time till the year 1177. our Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Hiſtorians make little mention of the <hi>Abiſſins,</hi> or any affairs of that Church: except <hi>Galviſius</hi> in his <hi>Opere chron. an. Chr.</hi> 451. <hi>fol.</hi> 462.</p>
            <p>But in the forementioned year 1177. Pope <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the III. was informed by one of his Phyſicians, named <hi>Peter,</hi> then newly returned out of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> that the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Emperor expreſſed himſelf very well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and deſirous of being reconciled to her Communion; for which purpoſe he requeſted his Holineſs to entertain ſome of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in <hi>Rome,</hi> where they might conveniently be brought up and inſtructed in the principles of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faith. This propoſal was readily embraced by the Pope, and the better to promote and encourage the deſigned Union he appointed them a certain houſe with a Chappel dedicated to S. <hi>Stephen,</hi> ſcituate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Quire of S. <hi>Peter's</hi> for their Accommodation. As ſoon as the Popes Letters brought Tidings into <hi>Ethiopia</hi> of the kind Reception allotted for them in <hi>Rome,</hi> many of the <hi>Abiſſins</hi> flocked thither, where they abode till they had throughly learnt and eſpouſed the Rites and cuſtoms of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, and then theſe New proſelytes were ſent home again ſit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to induce their Countreymen to a milder Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98035:7"/>
            <p>And to further this Deſign,<note place="margin">Vide Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan an. Ch. <hi>1253.</hi> N. <hi>3. 1321.</hi> N. <hi>3. 1329.</hi> N. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> which had ſo auſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a beginning, <hi>Innocent</hi> the <hi>IVth.</hi> ſent divers of the Order of S. <hi>Dominic</hi> into the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Territories, [to ſecond the endeavours of thoſe converted Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives now returned thither, and to perfect (if poſſible) the ſubjection of that Mighty Prince and people to the papal Chair.]</p>
            <p>Afterwards, <hi>Eugenius</hi> the <hi>IVth.</hi> having in the Council of <hi>Ferrara</hi> reconciled [at leaſt as was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended] the <hi>Greeks, Armenians,</hi> and <hi>Copties;</hi> [that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might be wanting to compleat ſo glorious an acqueſt,] ſent expreſs meſſengers to <hi>Zera Jacob</hi> then raigning in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> by whom he did earneſtly invite and ſolicit him to enter into the <hi>Catholick</hi> Communion: And he being loth to fruſtrate ſo tedious and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able an Embaſſy (eſpecially ſince twas the firſt made into thoſe parts by an European Prince) ſent ſome of his ſubjects to <hi>Rome,</hi> where they did not only comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Pope, but in their Emperor's name made a Confeſſion of Faith according to the Articles receiv'd and eſtabliſh'd in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and thereupon carried back with them Letters of Union from his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, as the Acts of that Council ſignifie, which was continued at <hi>Florence</hi> and ended in <hi>Rome;</hi> in the cloſe whereof this great affair was tranſacted, a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the death of Pope <hi>Eugenius.</hi> But the ſhort continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of that fair correſpondence, and the few acts of Union or Obedience put in practice thereupon, may ſufficiently evidence to the world that what the<note n="*" place="margin">A fair Confeſſion from a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</note> 
               <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Monarchs did of this nature in their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions with the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> was never heartily approved or generally entertained by their ſubjects.</p>
            <p>About this time <hi>John</hi> the II. King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98035:7"/>to make ſome new diſcoveries [that might em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy and inrich his Subjects, whoſe experience and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in the Art of Navigation extended their Renown and Dominion farther toward <hi>the Eaſt</hi> than any other People of <hi>Europe</hi> in that Age,] reſolved to ſend ſome able perſons with his Credential Letters, (as to the moſt remarkable Provinces thereabouts, ſo eſpecially) to the Emperor of <hi>Ethiopia;</hi> that, (if no other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage ſhould accrue thereby) he might at leaſt be gratified with a more exact Information concerning thoſe parts of the World. In this enterpriſe, <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus à Pavia</hi> and <hi>Johannes Petrus à Covilham,</hi> both <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueſes,</hi> were the chief: They began their Voyage from <hi>Lisbon</hi> on the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1486. and having paſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through <hi>Neapolis, Egypt, Tor,</hi> and <hi>Suaquem,</hi> at laſt <hi>Johannes (Alphonſus</hi> being dead by the way) arrived at the Imperial Court of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> where then raigned <hi>Alexander,</hi> who was Succeſſor to <hi>Bete Mariam</hi> the ſon of <hi>Zera Jacob,</hi> by whom they were entertained with all demonſtrations of Humanity and Kindneſs: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Johannes Petrus</hi> who grew into ſo much Favor and eſteem there, that he was never permitted to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into his own Countrey. He therefore omitted not, upon all fair Occaſions which his abode and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in that Court allowed him, to diſcourſe of the great Atchievements happily undertaken and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd by the Crown of <hi>Portugal;</hi> the relation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo won upon the mind of <hi>Hellen</hi> the Empreſs, that ſhe reſted not ſatisfied till an Embaſſy was ſent to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a League of Friendſhip with <hi>Emanuel,</hi> who then ſate on the Throne of his Father K. <hi>John</hi> deceaſed ſome time before. And on that errand one <hi>Matthew</hi> an <hi>Armenian,</hi> whom they made choice of as the fitteſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98035:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>perſon for ſuch an employment, came to <hi>Lisbon</hi> in the year 1513.</p>
            <p>This was the firſt Embaſſy which any Prince of <hi>Europe</hi> ever receiv'd from the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Court: For thoſe <hi>Abiſſins</hi> who were ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> upon the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Phyſician (as is before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated) came not immediately from <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> but were recommended from a Monaſtery which they then had in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon King <hi>Emanuel</hi> of <hi>Portugal</hi> returned an honourable Embaſſy to the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Emperor, which he committed to the management of <hi>Edward Galvan</hi> a very ſage experienc'd perſon, and <hi>Francis Alvarez</hi> his own Chaplain, a devout &amp; learned Prieſt; and with them ſent back the <hi>Armenian</hi> alſo. But <hi>Galvan</hi> dying in <hi>Cameran,</hi> an Iſle of the <hi>Red Sea, Rhoderic Lima</hi> was appointed his Subſtitute, who with <hi>Alvarez</hi> and the reſt of their company (except <hi>Matthew</hi> the <hi>Armenian</hi> who likewiſe dyed by the way) preſented themſelves at the Court of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> before <hi>David</hi> then raigning,<note place="margin">See the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Alva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez.</hi>
               </note> who gave them moſt ſplendid and obliging entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not only at their firſt Reception, but during the whole time of their Reſidence. After ſix years (a great part whereof they ſpent againſt their wills in that Court) they were licenſed to return, <hi>Alvarez</hi> having ſo well acquitted himſelf in his Negotiation there that the Emperor deputed him to be his Ambaſſador to the Pope, with a command [as was pretended] to tender Obedience to his Holineſs in his Name. But <hi>Claudius, David,</hi> ſucceſſor, did afterwards tell <hi>Oviedus</hi> to his face, that this was<note n="*" place="margin">This For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery is own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Pen of a Rom. Cath.</note> added to the Emperor's Letters as well contrary to his intention as without his knowledge. He ſent alſo with them <hi>Chriſtopher Licanatus, aliàs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98035:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Zega Zeab,</hi> with kind Letters both to the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> and the Pope.</p>
            <p>Theſe Embaſſadors left <hi>Ethiopia</hi> in the Month of <hi>April, an.</hi> 1526. and arrived at <hi>Lisbon</hi> in <hi>July</hi> the ſame year. But <hi>Francis Alvarez</hi> came not to <hi>Rome</hi> till the <hi>29th.</hi> of <hi>January, an.</hi> 1533. at which time he deliver'd the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Letters to the Pope (then <hi>Clemens</hi> the <hi>VIIth.</hi>) who cauſed them to be read in the preſence of that puiſſant Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Vth.</hi> and many other Worthies.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Emanuel</hi> was very deſirous this friendly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, already ſo well initiated, might be brought to perfection; and though he did not live to ſee his Wiſhes fully anſwer'd, yet this deſign of his was afterwards much facilitated by another Meſſage from <hi>Claudius</hi> the Son and Succeſſor of <hi>David,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he earneſtly requeſted aids from the King of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> againſt one<note n="*" place="margin">Againſt whom <hi>Tes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa Zion</hi> inveighs bitterly, terming him a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of the Goats and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor of the Sheep, becauſe of the deva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of his Native Countrey.</note> 
               <hi>Grain</hi> King of <hi>Adel,</hi> [a more ſucceſsful than potent Neighbour, who at that time miſerably waſted his Dominions,] and to render this requeſt the more ſucceſsful and avaialable, he [not only ſent a Confeſſion of his Faith ſince publiſhed by <hi>Job Ludolfus,</hi> but] in the ſame Letters further craved an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding perſon inveſted by the Pope with the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a <hi>Patriarch,</hi> and ſome other able Divines to be ſent under his Conduct into <hi>Abiſſinia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to this propoſal, <hi>John</hi> King of <hi>Portugal</hi> demanded of <hi>Ignatius de Loyola</hi> ſome Members of his Order (not long before inſtituted) to be employed on that occaſion; but the Father of the Jeſuits [with a Deliberation ſuitable to his Gravity] gave him no reply till the year 1555. and then he recommended <hi>Johannes Nunnius Barretta</hi> and <hi>Melchior Carnerius,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98035:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>both <hi>Portugueſes,</hi> and <hi>Andreas Oviedus</hi> a <hi>Caſtilian,</hi> as perſons throughly accompliſhed for ſuch a purpoſe. And [that a plenary power and qualification from the <hi>See Apoſtolick</hi> might add the more Honour and Authority to their Miſſion,] <hi>Nunnius</hi> was ordained <hi>Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> by Pope <hi>Julius</hi> the III<hi>d.</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards confirmed by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>IVth.</hi> and of his two Co-adjutors, the firſt was made Biſhop of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coea,</hi> the later Biſhop of <hi>Hierapolis:</hi> [Thus were they fitted to reconcile the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Church to the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith; and to prevent diſſention among them,] it was ordered and agreed that upon the death of <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Oviedus</hi> ſhould ſucceed in the Charge and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Patriarch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On this occaſion the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> wrote to <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius;</hi> and ſo did <hi>Ignatius Loyola,</hi> whoſe Epiſtle may be ſeen in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> However theſe Letters were not ſent by the three above named, but being conveyed to <hi>Petrus Maſcarenius</hi> then Vice-Roy of <hi>India,</hi> he tranſmitted them to the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Court by the hands of three other perſons, that they might ſound the Emperors Inclinations before the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> arrival: But <hi>Claudius</hi> (having already received the aids he deſired) had changed his mind in the matter of Religion, intending nothing leſs than to admit of the Alteration he had propoſed, ſo that, when the <hi>Roman</hi> Fathers came to preſs for Audience, he ſent them word, he had neither Need to receive the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, nor Will to obey the Authority of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> nay, ſo averſe were his Nobles to their Admiſſion, that ſome of them openly affirmed, they would ſooner ſubmit to the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> than the <hi>Roman</hi> yoke.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98035:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, that ſo high an enterpriſe might not fall under the blemiſh of an utter fruſtration, <hi>Oviedus</hi> [now become principal of the Miſſion, in the abſence of <hi>Nunnus,</hi> who proceeded not with them] boldly proſecutes his Journey with five Fathers more, and ſo wrought his way through all the Obſtacles which threatned his diſappointment, that on the third day of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> in the year 1557. they were admitted into the Emperor's preſence, who ſeemed to promiſe them a favorable Reception at the firſt; but having read their Letters, his Countenance was quickly changed, the Contents thereof being no way cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent to his Humor or Intereſt; as he afterwards ſufficiently expreſſed in his frequent diſputes with the Biſhop concerning Religion, whereby he gave them to underſtand he would not eaſily relinquiſh the receiv'd Opinions and Cuſtoms of the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Church. Hereupon <hi>Oviedus</hi> wrote a confutation of their Errors and preſented it to the Emperor, who made him no other reply thereunto than what might ſuffice to ſignifie his firm Reſolution of adhering to the Principles of his Forefathers.</p>
            <p>But theſe repeated altercations having rendred the Biſhop's preſence ingrateful at Court, he ſound it high time to retire with his Companions to ſome place of greater privacy, where they omitted not their uſual Induſtry and utmoſt endeavours to reduce the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Chriſtians to the Doctrine and Rites of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; whereupon the Emperor not only ſent him a ſevere check and prohibition, but (had not ſome of the Nobles interpos'd their intereſt and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) would have proceeded to put him to death, but [being diſſwaded from inflicting any Sanguinary
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98035:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>puniſhment,] he at laſt with great fury injoyned the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop never to ſee his face more. This was tranſacted in <hi>January</hi> 1559. and <hi>Claudius</hi> ended his days in a battle againſt the <hi>Saracens</hi> in the moneth of <hi>March</hi> next following.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Who in another Tract pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by my Author is alſo named <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Adamas Saghed</hi> his brother ſucceeded him both in the Throne, [and in the Reſolute Affection he had for the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Church, as then eſtabliſhed by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Laws and Conſtitutions of the Empire] being a man ſo inveterate againſt the Promoters of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cauſe</hi> that, upon ſome bold reply made by <hi>Ovie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> (when admitted to a Conference) he could ſcarce forbear laying violent hands upon him; nay, his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carried him ſo far as to tear the Gown from his back: Nor was his wrath thus appeaſed, but (when he was become Patriarch, in the room of <hi>Nunnius Barretta</hi> who dyed at <hi>Goa,</hi> in the year 1562.) he ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him into an horrid and deſolate Mountain to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his Complices, where they were confined for the ſpace of ſix moneths, till releaſed upon the Interceſſion of ſome Lords. He alſo revoked the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which <hi>Claudius</hi> his Predeceſſor had formerly granted, <q rend="inline">That ſuch <hi>Abiſſin</hi> women as were married to <hi>Portugueſes</hi> might obſerve the <hi>Roman</hi> Inſtitutions, without incurring any penalty:</q> and forbad all his Subjects on ſevere penalties to profeſs the <hi>Roman Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> or ſo much as be preſent at the <hi>Popiſh Maſs</hi> or any <hi>Portugueſs</hi> meeting; whereupon divers were impriſoned, tortured, and put to death, for tranſgreſſing the Imperial Edict.</p>
            <p>By this rigor and ſtrict ſeverity which he uſed for the ſuppreſſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Intereſt now ſet on foot by the Fathers in his Territories, many of his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98035:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Subjects were ſo<note n="‖" place="margin">Not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of the Jeſuits, who led the <hi>Portugal</hi> Faction.</note> exaſperated, that in the year 1560. <hi>Iſaac Barnagaſſi,</hi> who drew a conſiderable part of the Nobles into the Conſpiracy, <hi>plotted</hi> with thirty<note n="‖" place="margin">Not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of the Jeſuits, who led the <hi>Portugal</hi> Faction.</note> 
               <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugueſes</hi> how they might deſtroy him: And [finding no ſit Opportunity for the private Aſſaſſination of his perſon, the more plauſibly to effect it by open War] they pretend to vindicate the Right of <hi>Bencon</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>or</hi> Zar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car.</note> 
               <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car,</hi> the Son of his deceaſed Elder Brother <hi>Claudius,</hi> for whoſe advancement to the Throne they take up Arms. But <hi>Adamas,</hi> juſtly apprehenſive of the danger, ſoon levied an Army to ſuppreſs the<note n="*" place="margin">One Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the Pope's Agents.</note> Rebellion; and to re-ingratiate himſelf with the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> party, he invitos <hi>Oviedus,</hi> and the reſt of his Co-adjutors, by an amicable meſſage, to his Camp; [not being ignorant from what quarter the Storm aroſe.] How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the Fire being blown up ſo far already as not to be quenched without <hi>Effuſion of blond,</hi> they came to blows, with various ſucceſs: For, in the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict <hi>Adamas</hi> was driven from his Trenches, with ſome loſs; in the ſecond, he had the good fortune to take <hi>Tarcar</hi> alive, and (in hopes his Trouble might dye with him) cauſed him to be beheaded on the <hi>2d</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1561. But in a third Battel, <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the Traiterous Vice-Roy of <hi>Midrebahr,</hi> having ſet up another Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the deceaſed <hi>Tarcar,</hi> and called in the <hi>Turks</hi> to his Aid, ſo terrified <hi>Adamas</hi> and his Army with their great Guns, that he left his Camp in confuſed haſte and fled on the <hi>20th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1562. and in the moneth of <hi>February</hi> the year following, he ended his Days and Troubles together, leaving his Son<note n="‖" place="margin">Whom be elſewhere names <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilides.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Melec Saghed</hi> very young to ſucceed him, who, by thoſe of the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Party, was ſet up in his Fathers room.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Barnagaſſi,</hi> proſecuting the Rebellion upon the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98035:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Intereſt of <hi>Tarcar</hi>'s brother whom he had advanced to the Imperial Title and Dignity, became Maſter of <hi>Meſauva,</hi> and <hi>Erquiquum,</hi> with all the Sea-coaſt, which [finding himſelf unable to carry on the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he had begun, to its deſired iſſue] he maliciouſly betrayed to the ſubjection of the <hi>Turks,</hi> his Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates. However, in ſpite of the malice or ſucceſs of his Enemies, <hi>Melec Segued</hi> out-lived theſe Storms, and became equally eminent in Glory and Virtue.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Patriarch <hi>Oviedus,</hi> after the forementioned Diſcomfiture of <hi>Adamas,</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired with part of the <hi>Portugueſes</hi> [notwithſtanding their ſucceſs, which makes it very unaccountable] into <hi>Fremona,</hi> a Town in the Kingdom of <hi>Tigra,</hi> where he paſt the remainder of his life, he wrote di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Letters both to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> dated in the year 1562. wherein he chargeth the miſcarriage of his whole Enterpriſe on the want of Aids from <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> and (among other things) deſires to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> into <hi>India,</hi> which requeſt was granted him by a Brief from <hi>Pius quintus</hi> bearing date <hi>Feb.</hi> 25. 1566. But notwithſtanding this Liberty given him, he afterwards excuſed himſelf for not paſſing into <hi>India,</hi> by reaſon of the <hi>Turks</hi> who were become Maſters of the Paſſage, in Letters to the Pope on the <hi>15th</hi> of <hi>June</hi> 1567. wherein he alſo gave his Holineſs an Account, that the number of <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> at that time in the Empire of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> might be about five hundred. And at laſt this vigilant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch, after 15. or 16. years Reſidence in <hi>Fremona,</hi> dyed there, <hi>an.</hi> 1577. [After his death we find not any further attempt from <hi>Rome,</hi> till] the year 1584. when Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>XIIIth.</hi> ſent <hi>Johannes Baptiſta
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98035:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Brittus</hi> to reclaim <hi>Melec Saghed</hi> to Apoſtolick Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; [furniſhing him not only with perſwaſive Letters, but many Catholick Books, which for the more effectual Conviction both of the Soveraign and his Subjects, were to be diſperſed among them. Arm'd with theſe Inſtructions] he paſſed by the way of <hi>Aleppo</hi> to <hi>Ormuz,</hi> thence he ſailed to <hi>Goa,</hi> and there embarked himſelf on a ſhip bound for the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> where touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a ſmall Iſle (whoſe name we know not) he was taken and ſlain by the <hi>Turks, an.</hi> 1586. And yet [though he and the great deſign he undertook miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried together] ſome of his Books were brought into <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> where they were received and cried up [at leaſt by thoſe well affected to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>] as <hi>Divine Oracles</hi> dropt down from Heaven.</p>
            <p>Touching theſe Affairs we hear no farther men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion during the Raign of <hi>Melec Saghed;</hi> only that in the year 1593. he ſent one <hi>Tecle Maria,</hi> of the Order of S. <hi>Anthony,</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Lisbon,</hi> requiring ſuccors might be ſent him on ſome ſpecial occaſion; but his Meſſage was not anſwer'd with its deſired effect.</p>
            <p>About this time divers <hi>Roman</hi> Fathers made many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual attempts to paſs into <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> being ſtill diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the <hi>Turks,</hi> who were now<note n="*" place="margin">Thus they juſtly ſmarted by the Effect of their Treaſon againſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damas.</hi>
               </note> Poſſeſſors of all the Ports &amp; Avenues to that Empie lying on the Sea-coaſt, by whom ſome of them were killed and others captivated for many years. Hereupon they began to conſider of ſome ſafer Expedient for their Tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; it was concluded requiſite to this purpoſe that an Houſe ſhould be built upon <hi>Diu,</hi> an Iſle belonging to the Kingdom of <hi>Cambaya</hi> (ſcituate between the City <hi>Cambaya</hi> and the River <hi>Sinda</hi>) whereunto <hi>Armenians, Greeks, Arabs, Turks</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> continually reſort to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98035:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>lade and unlade the Traffick they carry on in thoſe parts; in regard that from thence, by reaſon of the great Concourſe of People always paſſng to and fro the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers might conveniently enough in the habit of <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> be conveyed by the <hi>Moors</hi> themſelves into <hi>Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> And no ſooner had <hi>Ayres de Saldanna,</hi> then Vice Roy of <hi>India,</hi> [of his pious inclination to that Religious deſign] built and endowed the Houſe they deſired, but this Counſel took effect, ſo that in the year 1603. <hi>P. Petrus Paez,</hi> in 1605. <hi>P. Anton. Fernandez.</hi> and <hi>P. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. de Angelis,</hi> and in 1606. <hi>P. Ludovicus de Azevedo</hi> and <hi>Laurentius Romanus,</hi> were ſucceſſively tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without danger or diſcovery: and [for the better diſperſing of their Doctrine] the one part betook themſelves to <hi>Dembea,</hi> and the other to <hi>Fremona;</hi> where [they knew ſo well to act their parts and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their advantages, that] they drew great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Proſelytes to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and among the reſt prevailed with the Emperor<note n="*" place="margin">Which perhaps is no other but the ſame <hi>Melec Sag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed</hi> under a different Title, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſual for the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſin</hi> Afo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs to have many Names, whereof <hi>Job Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolſus</hi> hath given apar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanco in his Notes on the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Claudius,</hi> N. <hi>5, 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Zà Dinghil</hi> himſelf to eſpouſe their Religion and own the Popes Authority. But [inſtead of winning his Subjects to embrace the ſame Profeſſion after the example of their Soveraign, his Defection from the eſtabliſhed Opinions and Practices of the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Church] ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged the people, [who till then had expreſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Loyal and Obedient to his Perſon and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment] that they<note n="‖" place="margin">This is a ſecond Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by Popiſh E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries.</note> rebelled againſt him, and while he endeavoured to reduce them to their Duty by force of Arms, he was ſlain in the Battel.</p>
            <p>After the death of <hi>Zà Dinghil,</hi> there aroſe two Competitors for the Crown, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Suſnejos,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween whom the whole ſtrength of the Empire was divided. <hi>Jacob</hi> had been driven, about a year before,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98035:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>by a Faction of the Nobles, to <hi>Enarea</hi> as an Exile, for as much as they reputed him to be Illegitimate; but having maintained a good correſpondence with divers of the Grandees during his abſence from Court, at his return he [found not only a very friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reception, but ſo great an Intereſt among them as enabled him to] overcome his Uncle <hi>Suſnejos</hi> in the Field and aſcend the Throne. But not long after [ſuch is the inſtability of Fortune] <hi>Suſnejos,</hi> who pretended to the Crown as nearer in Bloud reinforc'd his ſcatter'd Troops, and with his victorious Arms deprived <hi>Jacob</hi> at once of his Life and Soveraignty, on the <hi>10th.</hi> of <hi>March, an.</hi> 1607. This Prince <hi>Jacob</hi> had two ſons, who (upon their Fathers overthrow) fled for their ſecurity; the one was named <hi>Coſmus;</hi> the other, <hi>Zega Chriſtus,</hi> who, after he had eſcaped out of the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Territories, travelled to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> thence he went to <hi>Rome,</hi> after that he came to <hi>Paris,</hi> and in the end dyed at <hi>Ruel, an.</hi> 1638.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suſnejos,</hi> who was a Prince no leſs renowned for his Vertues than his Succeſſes, divided the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his three principal Kingdoms, <hi>Amhare, Abag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amider,</hi> and <hi>Tigra,</hi> between his three Brethren, and <hi>Gorgora</hi> he committed to the charge of a certain Duke, in whom he much confided. And having thus diſpoſed the places of greateſt Truſt into ſafe hands, he was the better able to ſuppreſs all Tumultuary Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the bud, and provided for the peace and ſafety of his Empire, which was much eſtabliſhed by his abſolute Conqueſt of a neighbouring enemy, that often infeſted his Dominions, called the <hi>Gallae.</hi> Theſe were a People inhabiting between the Kingdom of <hi>Bale</hi> and the Sea, generally eſteemed the Race of thoſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98035:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Jews</hi> that were irrecoverably diſperſed by <hi>Salmanaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar, Nebuch adnezzar, Titus, Adrian,</hi> and <hi>Severus,</hi> who, as they accidentally fell into thoſe parts, aſſociated to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and from ſmall deſpiſed beginnings grew up into a conſiderable body, which proved troubleſome (if not formidable) to the neighbouring Princes; though by their long abode in that Climate, they are now become black.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ethiopia</hi> being thus at reſt on every ſide, <hi>Suſnejos</hi> [reſolves to improve thoſe Haleyon days in propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating the Faith hitherto concealed in his own Breaſt, and for this purpoſe] calls the <hi>Roman</hi> Fathers, acquainting them with his deſign to be reconciled to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and expreſſing himſelf ready to let the Pope and King of <hi>Portugal</hi> know his Intentions by Letters, which he would have ſent without the privity of his Nobles. But the Fathers adviſing the contrary, he conſulted <hi>them</hi> in this Affair, though little to his ſatisfaction, they being utterly averſe to his Propoſal: However (notwithſtanding their diſſent) he reſolutely proceeds, and [following his own ſence] wrote to <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Vth.</hi> on the <hi>14th.</hi> of <hi>October,</hi> 1607. and to the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> on the <hi>10th.</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> the ſame year, in which Letters he requeſted Aids againſt his<note n="*" place="margin">He ſeems to intend ſuch of his Subjects as ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in the old <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſin</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion.</note> enemies, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to inſtruct his Subjects in the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith.</p>
            <p>Theſe [after a long delay] were granted him by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>XVth. an.</hi> 1622. (much about the time that the Colledge <hi>de propagandâ ſide</hi> was firſt erected in <hi>Rome</hi>) and <hi>Alphonſus Mendez,</hi> a <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Jeſuit, was conſtituted Patriarch of <hi>Ethiopia:</hi> But he departed not from <hi>Lisbon</hi> till the year 1624. when proſecuting his Voyage, he arrived the year follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98035:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>at the Port of <hi>Beilur</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Dancale,</hi> (which lies over againſt <hi>Mocca</hi>) the King whereof, being a Tributary and Ally to the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Emperor, had Notice of his arrival, and accordingly received him. From thence he paſt on to<note n="*" place="margin">Suppoſed the ſame with <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mona.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Maiguagua,</hi> where he winter'd with the Fathers of the Society; next he came to <hi>Genéte Jeſus,</hi> where alſo ſome Fathers dwelt; after that to <hi>Gorgora,</hi> and there he found Fathers like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and at laſt he arrived at the Emperor's Court, who entertained him with great demonſtrations of Joy and Favor.</p>
            <p>After a few days of refreſhment, the Patriarch <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus,</hi> attired in Pontifical habit, made a Sermon before the Court on that Text, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter,<note place="margin">S. Matth. <hi>16.18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and upon this Rock I will build my Church,</hi> &amp;c. And at the Cloſe of his Diſcourſe, the Emperor (by his Lord Chamberlain) made open Confeſſion in the preſence of all his Nobles, <q rend="inline">That <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> had been juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demend, and though <hi>Jacobus Syrus</hi> his Diſciple brought that Hereſie among them, yet they were ſtill conſcious of the Authority of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whereof himſelf was ſo throughly convinced that he reſolved to countenance the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith throughout all his Dominions; concluding with the Application of that Paſſage to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which S. <hi>Paul</hi> writes in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans, Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>cap.</hi> 8.35, 37, 38, 39.</note> 
                  <hi>Shall tribulation or diſtreſs, or perſecution, or famine, or naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or peril, or ſword,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>After this Speech was ended, the Emperor took an Oath, wherein he obliged himſelf to be an obedient Son to the Church and Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> then<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>or</hi> Baſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> 
               <hi>Faſila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> his Son and Heir apparent, did the like; and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98035:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>after him, <hi>Râs Secla Chriſtus</hi> the Emperor's half Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with other Grandees and Officers of State, took the ſame Oath. Then the Nobles ſwore Allegiance to <hi>Faſilades,</hi> as the ſole perſon whom [at the expence of their Lives and Fortunes] they would ſet upon the Throne, in caſe of his Fathers deceaſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſome [of the moſt zealous for the riſing Cauſe] added this Proviſo UPON CONDITION HE CONTINUED FIRM TO THE <hi>ROMAN</hi> FAITH.<note place="margin">☞</note> Laſt of all, the Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure of Excommunication was denounced againſt any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſhould thenceforward endeavour to remove the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith, or reſtore the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Perſwaſion. This great Revolution was tranſacted on the eleventh day of <hi>February,</hi> in the year 1626.</p>
            <p>In purſuance of the Oath he had lately taken, <hi>Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nejos</hi> required his Subjects to renounce their ancient Opinions and Way of Worſhip: But the major part of them were ſo obſtinate in their Old Principles, and their Soveraign ſo reſolute to reduce them to the New, that the whole Empire (lately flouriſhing in Peace and Tranquillity) was transformed into a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal ſcene of Oppreſſion and Violence, being filled with the bloud and ſlaughter of its native Inhabitants, inſomuch that the number of ſufferers in this Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of Religion did not ſeldom amount to four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in a day.</p>
            <p>This grand ſucceſs of the <hi>Roman</hi> Cauſe was with all convenient ſpeed certified to the Pope, then <hi>Urban</hi> the <hi>VIIIth.</hi> who (not a little pleaſed with ſuch acceptable tidings) wrote gratulatory Letters to the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Patriarch <hi>Alphonſus:</hi> dated at S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s in <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> 1628. and the fifth year of his Papacy.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98035:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>In the mean time all Acts of Religion paſſed in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> according to the rites of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; all from the Emperor to the meaneſt Commoner were re-baptized, and their Marriages, which the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Cuſtom had in times paſt allowed to be diſſoluble at the pleaſure of the parties, became now irevocable: [except a Divorce were granted by Diſpenſation, or adjudged by Sentence.]</p>
            <p>But, (to uſe my Author's own words <hi>hujuſmodi per vim &amp; ſupplicia populos ad Regnum Chriſtitrahendi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, diuturnus eſſe hautquaquam poterat;</hi>) this method of drawing (or rather driving) People by Acts of Violence and the infliction of puniſhments, to the Kingdom of<note n="*" place="margin">Though the <hi>Abiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins</hi> avere Chriſtians already.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was not likely to lay any laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foundation: For, when the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith had been promoted and maintained with Fire and Sword for the ſpace of<note n="*" place="margin">Four.</note> fourteen years, [ſo that it ſeemed to be rooted and eſtabliſhed in the Empire] divers of the Great ones (ſtill well affected to the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Church) combining together made an<note n="*" place="margin">A third Rebellion by reaſon of the Popiſh Intereſt.</note> Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Reſtauration and Defence of their Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Profeſſion; and theſe were quickly ſeconded by multitudes of the Common People flocking to them from every quarter, whoſe Courage and Numbers received no ſmall acceſſion from the preſence and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of thoſe <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Monks, who (leſt they ſhould have been compelled to embrace the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith or ſuffer the ſevere Penalties denounced againſt its oppoſers) had retired into inaceſſible Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, or lain hid in obſcure dens and caves; but now diſcloſed themſelves to the new raiſed Forces, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating them againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Fathers and their Doctrine.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98035:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>[<hi>Suſnejos</hi> in the mean time was not idle, but like a vigilant and reſolute Champion of the Faith he had ſolemnly eſpouſed, ſent forth his Troops to prevent the danger of thoſe Tumults, hoping to cruſh them ere they could be in a poſture to make head againſt him, though the ſucceſs did not anſwer his Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For] the Vice-Roy, to whoſe Valour and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct he entruſted that Campaign, and many Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Nobles who fought under his Banner, fell in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Battles; ſo that by the unhappy iſſue of theſe Inteſtine Wars the <hi>Catholick Cauſe</hi> daily declined, and upon the rumor of their loſſes the adverſe party pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably encreaſed both in ſtrength and number.</p>
            <p>Hereupon they firſt demand Liberty to celebrate their Maſs after the Rites preſcribed in the Liturgy of their Fore-fathers: This being readily aſſented to, the ſucceſs emboldned them to preſs with greater vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and earneſtneſs for the Reſtitution of all their other Opinions and Priviledges. And whereas the <hi>Roman</hi> Fathers ſeemed the ſole Obſtructors of their deſired Liberty, they never gave the Emperor any reſpit from their clamorous addreſſes till he conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to rid the Court of the Patriarch and his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operators, whereupon [being as well wearied by their Importunity as terrified by their Power] he commanded the Fathers to return to <hi>Maiguagua:</hi> Upon whoſe Removal from their Prince's eye, the people ſoon obtained a publick Revocation of all thoſe Edicts that had been made in favour of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> or their Religion, and a general Grant of Liberty of Conſcience to all the <hi>Abiſſins,</hi> as in times paſt. A ſhort time after, the death of <hi>Suſnejos</hi> put an end to the Controverſie, <hi>an.</hi> 1632.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98035:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Reaſons of the peoples implacable animoſity againſt the Fathers, which procured their Ejection, were not (it ſeems) well underſtood in <hi>Europe,</hi> till a certain <hi>Abiſſin</hi> named <hi>Abbas Gregorius,</hi> and he a Catholick, being weary of the Commotions occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in his own Countrey, came to <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> then to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and after that to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he gave an Account of the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon Oath before <hi>Don Pedro Lippa,</hi> then Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Colledge <hi>de propagandâ fide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Ernestus</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> hearing of this <hi>Abiſſins</hi> Arrival and Depoſition, immediately ſent an Expreſs to invite him to his Court, that he might be informed in a more particular manner from his own mouth. However, not being fully ſatisfied with his Relation, he ſent <hi>Wanſleben</hi> (my Author) into <hi>Egypt, an.</hi> 1663. to procure the beſt information he could from ſuch as came down from <hi>Ethiopia</hi> to <hi>Grand Cairo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now of the <hi>Abiſſins</hi> Relation and the Author's En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, this he gives us as the ſum and ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>The Patriarch <hi>Alphonſus Mendez,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Jeſuits Pride,</note> [as if he had vyed with the Emperor's Pomp and Attendance] maintained three hundred ſervants in his ordinary Retinue, and in all things carried a loſty Port far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding the degree of an Eccleſiaſtical perſon; (at leaſt among the <hi>Abiſſins,</hi> where men of that Function live at a contrary Rate and retein very different Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms;) nay, his Pride was ſuch that he would not give any <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> of what eſtate or degree ſoever, the reſpect due to his place or quality; whereof this may ſerve for one ſignal inſtance. <hi>Suſnejos,</hi> on ſome ſpecial occaſion, ſent his Son and Succeſſor to ſpeak
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98035:16"/>with the Patriarch, into whoſe preſence at the ſame inſtant came a Lay-brother of the Order; to the later he appointed a Chair, [as a mark of Honor,] per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the Heir apparent in the mean time to ſtand before him [without making him the leaſt Tender of the like Civility.] Nor did he put a leſs affront upon the Empreſs her ſelf, [when ſhe had as much Need as Reaſon to expect a more obliging Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;] for,<note place="margin">Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</note> whereas the Emperor had granted <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> and the Fathers of his Society the ſame Caſtle, wherein he preſerved his Treaſure, for their Security in the time of the Rebellion; they ingratefully denied admiſſion to his Royal Conſort, when (in a great apprehenſion of imminent danger) ſhe ſled thither for Refuge. And ſo little did he countenance the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of that Countrey, that he would neither allow any of the <hi>Abiſſins</hi> [though zealous Aſſertors of the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Profeſſion] the dignity of Holy Orders, nor permit them to accompany him in thoſe journeys which he rode on Horſe-back, except they would ſubmit to walk by him on foot, like ſo many Lacquies.</p>
            <p>[But, beſides theſe perſonal diſ-reſpects, there were many other Provocations, of a more hainous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which moved the <hi>Abiſſins</hi> to hate and expel the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> as enemies to the Publick Weal, in plotting the Subverſion as well of the Civil as Eccleſiaſtical Government, not content to Triumph in the Ruine of their <hi>Church,</hi> without improving <hi>that</hi> to the Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of their <hi>State</hi> too. For,]</p>
            <p>They laid a ſecret deſign to betray the Empire of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> to the <hi>Portugueſe</hi> Dominion;<note place="margin">and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Practices.</note> whereof they were undeniably convicted by divers Letters [writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98035:16"/>to carry on the <hi>Treaſon,</hi>] which were ſeaſonably intercepted.</p>
            <p>Under the pretence of building Churches and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, they raiſed Fortifications and ſtrong holds in many advantageous parts of the Countrey.</p>
            <p>And a vaſt quantity of Inſtruments for the erecting of Mounds and Bulworks, with other warlike pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, were (upon a ſtrict ſearch) found in their houſes.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, they did inordinately enrich themſelves and were intolerably inſolent; which firſt bred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Abiſſins</hi> a ſuſpicion, that they rather aimed at the Gold and Government of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> than the ſalvation of its Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>Upon this diſcovery, the <hi>Roman Cauſe</hi> dyed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Suſnejos;</hi> for no ſooner was his ſon <hi>Faſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lades</hi> advanced to the Throne, but he reſolved to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the <hi>Catholick</hi> Fathers out of his Dominions; and to the more violent as well as ſpeedy execution of this Reſolve he was not a little quickned by a meſſage from a neighbouring King, who, (being both Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and Wealthy) threatned to invade him, unleſs he gave his Subjects liberty to worſhip God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rites of their Anceſtors. Having therefore granted the Patriarch forty ſervants, Letters of ſafe Conduct, and licence to tranſport whatſoever his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had beſtowed upon him; he ſtrictly injoyns him and all the <hi>Roman</hi> Fathers to depart the Empire without delay, [and by publick Decree makes it a Capital Offence for any of them to be found in his Territories on any pretence whatſoever.]</p>
            <p>After their departure, he immediately prohibits the Exerciſe of the <hi>Roman Religion,</hi> deprives the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98035:17"/>Abiſſins</hi> of all their Honors and Charges; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels them both by Threats and Puniſhments to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their former Opinions; and in the Province of <hi>Aſſa</hi> put three <hi>Jeſuits</hi> to death, becauſe they departed not with the reſt, [at the day preſcribed:] The like number of <hi>Abiſſins</hi> and <hi>Portugueſes</hi> ran the ſame Fate [for their Obſtinacy,] and among others Biſhop <hi>Apollinaris;</hi> nor did he ſpare his own Uncle, <hi>Râs Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cla Chriſtus,</hi> then ſeventy years old, but condemned him to a tedious impriſonment.</p>
            <p>In a word, <hi>Suſnejos</hi> the Father was not more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and active to plant the <hi>Roman</hi> Faith in <hi>Abiſſinia,</hi> than <hi>Faſilades</hi> his Son and Succeſſor was to extirpate and aboliſh it.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as theſe affairs were throughly made known and impartially ſtated at <hi>Rome;</hi> the Colledge <hi>de propagandâ fide</hi> [upon mature conſideration of their ill ſucceſs and its as juſt as apparent occaſion] reſolve to lay aſide the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> as improper inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for that enterpriſe, and in their ſtead made choice of ſome Religious perſons of the Order of <hi>Mendicant Friers</hi> to manage their deſign upon <hi>Ethiopia.</hi> Accordingly certain <hi>Capuchins</hi> (namely <hi>Agat-Angelus</hi> and <hi>Caſſianus</hi>) were deputed for that Charge, and order'd to proceed on their journey thither, <hi>an.</hi> 1636.</p>
            <p>While theſe things were tranſacted in <hi>Italy,</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria</hi> (at the Requeſt of <hi>Faſilades,</hi> who in the year 1634. had re-ſetled his Empire in its priſtine State and Condition) had ordained one <hi>Arminius</hi> a <hi>Copti,</hi> of the Monaſtery of S. <hi>Macarius,</hi> Metropolitan of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> according to the ancient uſage; whom the <hi>Italian Friers,</hi> upon their arrival at <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> found ready to depart to his new
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98035:17"/>Charge, as ſoon as he ſhould receive the Patriarch's Benediction and his Letters Patents: and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that they were alſo deſigned for <hi>Abiſſinia,</hi> he made the Fathers a civil invitation to be his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in Travel; but <hi>Arminius</hi> having obtained his diſpatches before they were fitted for ſo great a journey, proceeds on his way without them.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time there was in <hi>Cairo</hi> one <hi>Peter Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> a <hi>Lutheran</hi> of <hi>Lubec,</hi> who, for his better ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> paſſed under the name of <hi>Petrus Nolingus,</hi> an <hi>Hollander.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">An En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe worthy of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</note> This man (as is credibly reported) with Ten others of the ſame Perſwaſion, [emulating the induſtry of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church,] concurred in a joynt reſolution to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe the Chriſtian Doctrine, according to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> over the whole earth; [and that the diſtribution of their Labours might be the better regulated, they caſt the ſeveral Provinces of the World into a proportionable divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion among them,] each of them obliging himſelf to undertake that part which ſhould fall to him by Lot: In purſuance of which agreement and deſign, the forenamed <hi>Peter</hi> was advanced as far as <hi>Cairo,</hi> The Lot having deſtined <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Ethiopia</hi> to his charge. A perſon (by my Authors own confeſſion) of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Prudence, well skilled in Hiſtory, experienc'd in Phyſick, and in many Languages (as <hi>Greek, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, Arabic, Ethiopic,</hi>) inferiour to none.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Cairo</hi> he travelled ſevent days journey to <hi>Siút,</hi> a City in the upper <hi>Egypt,</hi> but was conſtrained to return thence by the means of <hi>Agat-Angelus;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prevent the like affront and diſappointment a ſecond time, he determined to procure Licence to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98035:18"/>accompany <hi>Arminius</hi> the <hi>Ethiopick Metropolitan</hi> in his journey towards his new Province, for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that he might ingratiate himſelf with the chief of the <hi>Copties</hi> [at leaſt as my<note n="*" place="margin">With thoſe of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion 'tis no ſin to bely an Heretick to blaſt his Reputation</note> Author ſaith] he not only profeſſed their Religion, but privately ſuffer'd himſelf to be Circumciſed, and by theſe means ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained commendatory Letters from the <hi>Alexandrian Patriarch</hi> to the Emperor of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> as well as Permiſſion to joyn with <hi>Arminius</hi> in his Travels, who left <hi>Cairo</hi> in the year 1637.</p>
            <p>[And yet the Co-herence of my Author's diſcourſe ſeems to imply that <hi>Heylings</hi> great parts and abilities recommended him to <hi>Arminius;</hi> who, that he might the better veil his own want of Learning under the covert of ſuch a mans company and aſſiſtance, had a private inducement to obtain the <hi>Patriarch</hi>'s Grant for his Protection and Society, without having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to any ſuch indirect means or baſe complian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as are above ſpecified.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Heyling</hi> thus arrived in <hi>Abiſſinia,</hi> under the <hi>Metropolitans</hi> Favour, took up his abode in a Church, [not far from Court.] And as ſoon as he was ſetled in his new Manſion, he began to practiſe <hi>Phyſick</hi> and profeſs the Inſtruction of Youth in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew tongues,</hi> wherein he quickly became ſo famous that even the principal Nobility accounted it a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular priviledge to have their Sons educated under his Tuition; ſo that he might eaſily have amaſſed a very conſiderable Treaſure, had he been diſpoſed to accept or hoord up all the Gratuities that were offer'd him: But he either generouſly refuſed the Preſents when tendered, or elſe (in eaſe they were urgently preſſed upon him) liberally diſtributed the over-plus
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98035:18"/>among the poor; [after he had made himſelf a very moderate allowance out of it for Food and Raiment.] A ſufficient evidence [as my Author notes] of his great Abſtinence or ſelf-denial.</p>
            <p>Theſe remarkable qualities and endowments could not long brook the concealment of a private life, but brake out into ſuch an advantageous report of him as reached the Emperors Ears, and won him ſo high an eſteem at Court that [after ſome Trial had been made of his Capacity for publick employments] he was by large ſteps and degrees quickly raiſed to the principal Charge of the Empire, in which great Office and Truſt he acquitted himſelf with ſuch a prudent addreſs, that his Great Maſter obliged him (with a courteous violence) to accept of a Revenue and Attendance equal to the Chief of the Nobility, with a moſt delightful Apartment in a place (accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Paradiſe of <hi>Ethiopia</hi>) called <hi>Genéte Chriſtos;</hi> yea, and deſigned him, as 'tis commonly and poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively affirmed, his own Daughter in marriage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Heyling</hi> ſinding himſelf ſo deeply intereſted in the Prince's Favour and Affection, began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind his Imperial Majeſty of all thoſe deplorable Troubles wherein his Dominions had been ſo often involved [(eſpecially in the days of his Father,) and ſo effectually repreſented to him that thoſe dreadful Commotions and all their pernicious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences] were ſolely occaſioned by the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Emiſſaries,</hi> warning him of the ſudden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of others on the ſame Errand, [together with the firm Reſolution of their Party to perſiſt in the like <hi>Treaſonable</hi> attempts,] that at laſt his Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance prevailed with the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> Monarch and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98035:19"/>his Council to eſtabliſh a Penal Law againſt all<note n="*" place="margin">With re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard (no doubt) to a certain old Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which our learned Dr. <hi>Ed. Caſtelcites</hi> out of <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doval</hi> thus, <hi>Que gente blanca ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziendo los labradores los han de echar ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra de Eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia:</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting, That a White Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe ſhould diſpoſſeſs them of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</note> the people of <hi>Europe,</hi> [of what Countrey or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion ſoever,] forbidding any perſon bearing the native diſtinction of a <hi>white Complexion</hi> to enter his Territories upon pain of death.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the <hi>Roman</hi> Fathers, <hi>an.</hi> 1638. proceed on their journey by <hi>Suaquem</hi> an (Iſle of the <hi>Red Sea</hi>) thence to <hi>Enquiquum</hi> and ſo on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Court, in the Company of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Merchants who had liberty of Traffick in thoſe parts. When they came to <hi>Seráve,</hi> where <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſſi</hi> the Vice-Roy of <hi>Midrebahr</hi> had his ordinary Reſidence, he no ſooner ſaw two White Faces a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Travellers, but he ſuſpected them to be ſuch as had by the late Imperial Edict been baniſhed from all the Coaſts of <hi>Ethiopia:</hi> whereupon (being thereunto adviſed by the chief <hi>Abisſin</hi> Prieſt upon the place) he ſearched their Sumpture, and therein found Chalices, Stones conſecrated for Altars, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal Ornaments and Maſs-Books, with other things prepared for Eccleſiaſtical uſes. Having thus diſcovered their perſons and deſigns, the Vice-Roy informs his Maſter of the diſcovery he had made, and detains the Fathers in chains until he ſhould receive further notice of his Majeſties pleaſure; which was no ſooner ſignified but they were brought to the Emperor's preſence on the <hi>5th.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1638. where, upon reading ſome Letters which they produced from the Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the Emperor was at firſt inclined to remand them [without any further mark of his diſpleaſure] to <hi>Grand Cairo</hi> from whence they came: But, being adviſed to the contrary by <hi>Peter Heyling,</hi> and his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98035:19"/>new Metropolitan <hi>Arminius,</hi> he changed his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and required them [as a Teſt reſolved on in the late Conſult] to receive the Holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after the manner preſcribed and practiſed in the <hi>Abisſin</hi> Church, with a Promiſe that (in caſe of their Conformity thereunto) they ſhould not only have Licence to remain in his Dominions, but be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of places of Honour and Truſt therein: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided alſo that they bleſs <hi>S. Dioſcorus,</hi> and curſe Pope <hi>Leo;</hi> for, all the <hi>Abisſins</hi> firmly believe, that in his time the <hi>Roman</hi> Church fell into <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and (to let my Author ſpeak in his own Language, <hi>Ex ſancta &amp; capite, qualem tune fuiſſe fatentur, eam factam dicunt Caudam &amp; Cathedram Diaboli</hi>) from being Holy and the Head (as they then owned her) ſhe became, they ſay, the Tail and the Chair of the Devil.</p>
            <p>This propoſal being utterly rejected by the Friers, his Imperial Majeſty (at the urgent motion of his Mother, the Clergy, and the Commons, whoſe joynt Vogue accuſed him of Diſſimulation, in caſe he put not theſe <hi>Franks</hi> to death according to his own Decree) paſt ſentence againſt them; which was ſpeedily executed, they being hanged with thoſe very Ropes which themſelves had made uſe of for their Girdles, and in that poſture were intombed by the vaſt number of Stones which the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of <hi>Abisſin</hi> Zealots threw at them; [the heap ſtill remaining a Monument as well of the Roman Fathers Reſolution as of Ethiopian ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Heyling</hi> in proceſs of time (being grown very Rich and powerful) began to make publick
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98035:20"/>expreſſion of his diſlike of divers <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Cuſtomes, decrying eſpecially their Adoration of Saints, and of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelf, as repugnant to true Religion and the Holy Scriptures; having on the ſame account privately forbidden his Scholars to uſe their ordinary Forms of Prayer directed to her. This begat him much ill will and great oppoſition among the Nobles; for all the <hi>Abiſſins</hi> have a very great Reverence for the Holy Virgin: To expreſs their diſguſt therefore, they firſt withdrew their Sons from his Tuition; and after that, made uſe of their beſt Arguments and Intereſt with the Emperor not only to remove him from Court but out of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions alſo, who hereupon having gently admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him [at leaſt to be ſilent and connive at their Cuſtoms, if he could not conform to them] without effect, orders him to quit his Territories for a time, as the beſt expedient to avoid the dangerous efforts of popular fury.</p>
            <p>Thus this Great man voluntarily relinquiſhed <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> together with the High place and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt he held there, after he had been (as it were) na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turallized by Twelve years Reſidence in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; being accompanied by his uſual Retinue, and all the Wealth he had gotten, [which was ſent along with him as a mark of the juſt eſteem and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Emperor ever had for him:] But having advanced on his way thus attended as far as the Iſle <hi>Suaquem,</hi> he fell into the hands of a <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Paſha, who (to ſatisfie his Avarice) deprived him at once of his Life and Riches.</p>
            <p>Soon after <hi>Peter Heyling</hi>'s departure,<note place="margin">Another Popiſh Plot.</note> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors younger Brother, with divers Nobles inclin'd
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98035:20"/>to the Roman Principles, made a dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt their natural Lord, upon the deſign of introducing more of the Catholick Fathers; but <hi>Faſilades,</hi> having received timely notice hereof from <hi>Arminius,</hi> his Primate and Metropolitan, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately cauſed his Brother to be<note n="*" place="margin">Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the barbarous Cuſtom of Eaſtern Tyranny.</note> Strangled with a Napkin [for the better prevention as well of publick Rumors as Commotions] and expoſed his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices to open Execution. And, [in conſideration of this <hi>Treaſon,</hi>] became ſo exaſperated againſt the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> that he rather reſolved to introduce <hi>Mahumetaniſm</hi> than admit any of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church into his Territories. This Reſolution [raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceived to avoid one extream, did deſperately precipitate him into another, wherein] he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſo far that (as my Author ſaith) he ſent to <hi>Iman,</hi> a certain King of <hi>Arabia Felix,</hi> for a <hi>Turk</hi> learned in the Law of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> whoſe Abilities might qualifie him to tranſport the Doctrine of his Prophet into <hi>Ethiopia.</hi> But an <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Chriſtian, being one of thoſe that were employ'd on this Errand, as ſoon as he returned (whether upon diſguſt, or ſome other more laudable reaſon) imparted to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal of the Nobility and Clergy the ſum of that wicked Embaſſy, adviſing them to conſider of ſome prudent and ſafe way for the prevention of ſo great a miſchief.</p>
            <p>Upon this Information they began to raiſe tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary Aſſemblies, wherein the people grew ſo bold as to vent open threats againſt their Soveraign; nay, when the Turkiſh <hi>Effendi</hi> arrived, they did ſo much ſtomach the honourable reception he found at Court, that they twice ſet his Lodgings on Fire, and ſpared
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98035:21"/>not to make ſundry Attempts upon his Life. Theſe daring Actions, pretending no leſs than the abſolute revolt of his Subjects, engaged <hi>Faſilades</hi> (under the pretext of ſome criminal Accuſation) to caſt the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Embaſſador into priſon, and declare himſelf ignorant of the deſign for which he came into his Dominions. Soon after [finding it the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mean to allay the Commotions and reſtore the Peace of his Empire] he ſent the <hi>Turk</hi> back into his own Countrey, having gratified him with many rich Preſents, among which was a very coſtly Veſt beſtowed on him by the Empreſs.</p>
            <p>The Colledge <hi>de propagandâ fide,</hi> having all this while received no News of the Fathers <hi>Capuchins</hi> ſince their departure, ſent after them other Fathers, <hi>an.</hi> 1638. whereof <hi>P. Antonius de Virgolta,</hi> and <hi>P. Antonius de Petra Pagana,</hi> were the Chief, both being of the Reformed Order of <hi>S. Francis.</hi> Theſe Emiſſaries paſſing by <hi>Grand Cairo,</hi> ſoon after arrived at <hi>Suaquem</hi> and thence ſailed to <hi>Meſauva,</hi> where they remained two years [in continual expectation of ſome favourable opportunity for their ſafe paſſage into <hi>Ethiopia:</hi>] But having endured many Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the injurious <hi>Turks</hi> in the time of their abode there, [and nothing advanced in the hopes of compaſſing their deſign,] they were neceſſitated to return to <hi>Suaquem;</hi> an Iſle whoſe ſhores are ſo very white that they ſeem at a diſtance cover'd with Snow, much about a mile in compaſs and well inhabited, but doth not yield the leaſt drop of freſh water, wherewith it is ſupplied from the neighbouring Continent, though at a dear rate; for, a skin of water is commonly ſold for two Chabers, forty of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98035:21"/>which pieces amount to the value of a Spaniſh Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, neither doth it produce any Fruits or Food for the uſe of Man, (nay, it cannot boaſt of the leaſt Verdure) but is furniſhed with all Neceſſaries for humane Life from the Kingdoms of <hi>Fungi</hi> and <hi>Sennaar.</hi> In this Iſle <hi>Antonius de Petra Pagana</hi> practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Phyſick, and <hi>Antonius de Virgolta</hi> made Fans of Straw, by which means they lived quietly and ſupplied their Wants in that barren place.</p>
            <p>There Father <hi>Anthony Virgolta</hi> dyed, whereupon Father <hi>Anthony de Petra</hi> (now left alone) ſends Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to <hi>Rome</hi> wherein he informed the Colledge that to ſeek for any acceſs into <hi>Abiſſinia</hi> by Sea would be not only a fruitleſs but impoſſible Attempt.</p>
            <p>Hereupon they ſend other Emiſſaries with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to proceed all the way by Land, wherein they were order'd to go as far as conveniently they might by the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> then to paſs on through <hi>Nubia, Sennaar,</hi> and the whole Realm of <hi>Fungi,</hi> and ſo to ſteal privately into <hi>Ethiopia. Jacob Vemmers,</hi> a Carmelite Frier, was Head of the Miſſion. And, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſtituted <hi>Apoſtolick Vicar</hi> of the whole Empire, departed from <hi>Rome, an.</hi> 1640. with Letters from Pope <hi>Urban</hi> VIII. to the Emperor, the Metropolitan, and <hi>Archi-mandrita</hi> the General of the Monks, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively: his Companions were <hi>P. Joſeph de Atino,</hi> and <hi>P. Felix de S. Severino,</hi> of the Reformed Order of S. <hi>Francis.</hi> But upon the death of <hi>Vemmers, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus de Caſtro</hi> ſucceeded in his Charge, who, when he was advanced on the way with his companions as far as <hi>Cairo,</hi> returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> [for what reaſon is not ſpecified in our Hiſtory.]</p>
            <p>While <hi>Matthaeus</hi> was haſtning towards <hi>Italy,</hi> the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98035:22"/>Fathers, whom he left in <hi>Egypt,</hi> had an opportunity preſented for their conveyance to <hi>Suaquem,</hi> by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour they had gained with <hi>Mahunied-Paſha</hi> who was then going to aſſume the Government of that Iſland with ſome other adjacent places. Their arrival there did very much revive and comfort <hi>P. Antonius de Petra,</hi> [till then diſconſolate in that melancholy So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude wherein the death of <hi>Virgolta</hi> had left him.]</p>
            <p>Soon after they held a Conſultation there concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the method and poſſibility of their gaining en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into <hi>Abiſſinia,</hi> whereupon they reſolved firſt to found the Emperor's inclinations by Letters, and theſe they wrote by the Aid of a certain <hi>Catholick Abiſſin</hi> named <hi>Gregory,</hi> who had been [graced with the ſingular favour of being] ordained a Prieſt by the Patriarch <hi>Alphonſus Mendez.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But theſe Letters, being delivered to <hi>Faſilades</hi> at that unhappy juncture of time when the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Doctor was in <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> put him into ſuch a rage, that he preſently diſpatched a Meſſenger to the Paſha, then reſident in <hi>Suaquem,</hi> requeſting him to kill all the Religious men in his Iſle, and (to render this cruel demand the more prevalent) promiſed 150. Ounces of Gold for his Reward. This taking pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal was readily accepted by the covetous Paſha (Succeſſor to him that brought the Fathers thither from <hi>Cairo</hi>) who [to purchaſe both the Money and Favour of ſo Potent a Neighbour] cut off their heads almoſt as ſoon as the <hi>Abiſſin</hi> Meſſenger arrived; for, [without any further warning or legal Proceſs,] they were executed in the Evening of that very day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Emperor's Letters came to his hands, which is ſaid to be the Feaſt of the <hi>Annunciation, an.</hi> 1648.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98035:22"/>
            <p>From that time till the year 1669. the <hi>Roman Colledge,</hi> [upon theſe apparent hazards and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,] quitted their Deſigns of propagating the <hi>Catholick Faith</hi> in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> during the Raign of <hi>Faſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lades:</hi> but then, having News of his death, upon ſome hopes or intimation that his Succeſſor was leſs rigorous towards the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed their former Intentions, and made choice of theſe three Prieſts to be their Emiſſaries, <hi>Don An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio de Andrada</hi> a Native of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> and two Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Order of St. <hi>Francis;</hi> who [in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Directors of their Miſſion, ſo diligently proſecuted their Journey, that without any remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able impediment they] arrived at <hi>Suaquem,</hi> the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Iſle aforenamed, as their laſt Letters intimate; [where we muſt leave them and their Enterpriſe, till my Author, or ſome other able Pen, ſhall give us a further Account of its Succeſs.]</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
